Finding Aid for Michigan Nature Association records, 1945-2013
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Nature Association records 1945-2013, 1961-1999
Michigan Nature Association.
7 linear feet
93844 Aa 2
The Michigan Nature Association is a non-profit organization concerned with nature education and the purchase and maintenance of land throughout the state for the establishment of natural sanctuaries. The record group includes early papers of the organization, administrative files, correspondence, property and land files, topical files, publications, some visual materials, and legal materials associated with their opposition to the construction of transmission lines in a nature sanctuary.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The record group was the gift of the Association (donor no. 8167 ) and came to the library in 1993 with a major accession in 2004.
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The record group is open to research.
The Michigan Nature Association has its origins as a "bird watching group." In 1952, moved to protest the destruction of the common tern colony at Metropolitan Beach in Macomb County, the group, lead by Bertha Daubendiek, was incorporated as the St. Clair Metropolitan Beach Sanctuary Association. In 1955, the organization changed its name to the Macomb Nature Association and established the Junior Nature Patrol division. The purpose of the Nature Patrol was to emphasize nature education in public schools through the use of presentations and field trips.
In 1960, realizing that education was not enough to preserve nature areas within fast growing Macomb County, the Association decided to assume debt to buy five natural areas to be called nature sanctuaries. With this debt quickly paid off, more nature sanctuaries were acquired, through purchase and donation. The organization's rapid growth, activities, and participation in local environmental issues led to its renaming in 1965 to the Eastern Michigan Nature Association and in 1970 to the Michigan Nature Association.
The MNA's purpose is twofold: to carry on a program of natural history study and conservation education; and to acquire, maintain, and protect nature sanctuaries, natural areas, and plant preserves in the state of Michigan.
The Michigan Nature Association records include early papers of the organization, administrative files, correspondence, property and land files, topical files, publications, some visual materials, and legal materials associated with their opposition to the construction of transmission lines in a nature sanctuary. The record group has been arranged into the following series: Early papers, Administrative, Correspondence, Topical files, Publications, Visual Materials, Bertha Daubendiek personal papers, and Litigation files. Most of these files were maintained by Bertha Daubendiek, a founder and secretary-treasurer of the organization.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Daubendiek, Bertha A. (Bertha Antoine); Environmental protection--Michigan.; Michigan Nature Association.; Detroit Edison Company.; Natural areas--Michigan.; Eastern Michigan Nature Association.; Macomb Nature Association.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Land--Michigan.; Michigan--Land.; Michigan Nature Association.; Michigan--Parks.; Natural areas--Michigan.; Parks--Michigan.
Genre Terms:
Videotapes.
- Early papers 1952-1969
  The Early Papers series (0.5 linear feet) contains the records created by the Association as it was first the St. Clair Metropolitan Beach Sanctuary Association, then the Macomb Nature Association, and then the Eastern Michigan Nature Association. These records provide a comprehensive portrait of the organization during each period. They include financial reports, correspondence, meeting minutes, announcements, and memoranda.
  - St. Clair Metropolitan Beach Sanctuary Association 1952-1954, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Macomb Nature Association 1955-1964, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Eastern Michigan Nature Association 1965-1969, 2 folders (Box 1)
- Administrative
  The Administrative series (0.5 linear feet) contains bylaws and revisions, articles of incorporation, meeting minutes, legal papers pertaining to trust agreements, stocks, and taxes, undated and fragmentary membership lists, financial reports, and records of land and monetary support. The bulk of the meeting minutes is from 2000-2002.
  - Articles of Incorporation (Box 1)
  - Bylaws (Box 1)
  - Policy Handbook 2002 (Box 1)
  - Legal Papers 1979, 1992-2000 (Box 1)
  - Meeting Minutes 1969-2004, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Financial Reports 1964-1979 (Box 1)
  - Land Donations (Box 1)
  - Monetary Donations (Box 1)
  - Membership Lists (Box 1)
- Correspondence and other papers undated, 1970-2005
  The Correspondence series (1.5 linear feet) dates from 1960-2005, with the bulk from 1993-1999. It consists of letters to and from volunteers, potential donors and MNA employees, and illustrate the day-to-day operations of the Association. The bulk of the records were written by and addressed to the founder and long-time executive secretary Bertha Daubendiek.
  - Undated and fragmentary (Box 1)
  - 1970-1973, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - 1974-1997, 30 folders (Box 2)
  - 1998-2005, 15 folders (Box 3)
- Property and Land
  The Property and Land series (0.5 linear feet) contains records related to land prospects, assessments, and acquisition. It includes property to see, property reports submitted by volunteers along with their recommendations, proposed land contracts, monthly field goals for identifying natural flora on new land prospects, sanctuary lists, and plant surveys taken of existing nature sanctuaries.
  - Chronological List of Blooms (Box 3)
  - Land Contracts (Box 3)
  - Property Reports (Box 3)
  - Land Prospects
    - Avrill Williams Property (St. Clair County) 1992 (Box 3)
    - Cass Lake (Oakland County) (Box 3)
    - Colic Root Prairie 1997 (Box 3)
    - Dutchman's Breeches (Genesee County) (Box 3)
    - Klimowicz Property (St. Clair County) 2003 (Box 3)
    - McKinley Park (Genesee County) 1997 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Mitten Lake (Mackinac County) (Box 3)
    - Mud Lake (St. Clair County) (Box 3)
    - Mulligan Plains (Marquette County) 1996 (Box 3)
    - Pine Run Creek (Box 3)
    - Ronald Joseph Property (Genesee County) (Box 3)
    - Scappiticci Property (Genesee County) 1996 (Box 3)
    - Sibley Road (Wayne County) (Box 3)
    - Slater Road (Oakland County) 1997 (Box 3)
    - Thompson Road (Genesee County) 1997 (Box 3)
    - Troy Schools (Oakland County) (Box 3)
    - Zucker Property (Lapeer County) (Box 3)
  - Plant Survey
    - Harsens Island 1996 (Box 3)
    - Moore Woods (St. Clair County) (Box 3)
    - Port Huron Game Area (St. Clair County) (Box 3)
    - McLaughlin Prairie 1979 (Box 3)
    - St. Clair County Sanctuaries 1985 (Box 3)
    - Sanctuaries 1985 (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - Monthly Field Goals undated (Box 3)
  - Michigan's Special Plants (Box 3)
  - A Scientific Look at the Native Flora and Fauna of Genesee Country as of February 28, 1997 (Box 3)
  - Sanctuary Lists (Box 3)
  - Want Lists (Box 3)
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (1 linear feet) series reflects the various activities that the MNA has participated in. It includes fundraising efforts for the Van Dusen Endowment Challenge, grant applications for the Chevron Conservation Award, its participation in the Pigeon River Defense Coalition, its endangered species proposal, sanctuary dedication announcements, and memoranda sent to the volunteer exploratory group. The series also contains the study course given for the Association's tenth anniversary and a transcription of the slide presentation given in commemoration of its fiftieth anniversary. There are also records of the Junior Nature Patrol, the results of a spray survey conducted in petition to preserve a Natural Beauty Road, and a diary detailing the activities performed by an MNA member.
  - Chevron Conservation Award 2001 (Box 3)
  - Diary, MNA Activities performed by John Sohlden, Oakland Co. 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Explorers Group Memoranda 1992-1995 (Box 3)
  - Fiftieth Anniversary 2003 (description of slide presentation) (Box 3)
  - Junior Nature Patrol 1952 (Box 3)
  - Maps, miscellaneous (Box 4)
  - Michigan Endangered Species proposal 1977 (Box 4)
  - Pigeon River Defense Coalition 1977 (Box 4)
  - Sanctuary Dedications (Box 4)
  - Spray survey 1970 (Box 4)
  - Tenth Anniversary study course 1962 (Box 4)
  - Travel report and expenses 1988 (Box 4)
  - Van Dusen Endowment Challenge 1991-1994, 2 folders (Box 4)
- Publications
  The Publications series (1 linear foot) contains the monthly mailings sent to members between 1971-1983, newsletters, newspaper articles written about the MNA or current environmental issues of concerned, press releases related to upcoming public meetings, field trips, and events, and brochures. It also includes the books and sanctuary guides which the MNA has published for sale.
  - Membership Mailings 1971-2013, 6 folders (Box 4)
  - Newsletters 1964-2013, 4 folders (Box 4)
  - Newspaper Articles, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Press Releases 1992-1998 1995 (Box 4)
  - Sanctuary Guides 1968, 1977, 1983, undated (Box 5)
  - The Birds of St. Clair Metropolitan Beach Wildlife Sanctuary, undated (Box 5)
  - The Nature Year in Macomb and St. Clair Counties, Michigan, 1963 (Box 5)
  - From Sawmill to Sanctuary: The Estivant Pines Story by Charles Eshbach, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Walking Paths in Keweenaw, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Wing Lake Road 1978, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - Informational and promotional, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Brochures (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Visual materials
  The Visual Materials series contains a video recording and photographs. The video recording In Our Trust was produced by the MNA and the photographs were found undated, unidentified, and scattered throughout the record group.
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Videocassette: In Our Trust; A Look at the Michigan Nature Association, 1991 (Box 5)
- Bertha Daubendiek personal papers
  The Bertha Daubendiek personal papers series (0.2 linear ft.) includes a personal scrapbook of a vacation trip, awards and citations, and miscellaneous
  - Scrapbook (Box 5)
  - "Life and History of W. H. Daubendiek from October 18, 1868 to August 10, 1897" (Box 5)
  - Citations and awards (Box 5)
  - Correspondence to family and friends (selection) (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 5)
- Litigation files
  The Litigation Files series (2 linear feet) consists of legal documents and related papers from the MNA participation in the suit of In the Matter of the Detroit Edison Company (Greenwood Energy Center Units 2 and 3) in the 1970s. In this case, the MNA fought the proposed placement of transmission lines through a nature sanctuary.
  - In the Matter of the Detroit Edison Company (Greenwood Energy Center Units 2 and 3) 1973-1978 (Box 6)
    (regarding opposition of MNA to placement through a nature sanctuary of transmission lines)
  - In the Matter of the Detroit Edison Company (Greenwood Energy Center Units 2 and 3) 1973-1978 (Box 7)
    (continued)